Tamara Paula Temple

Webologist and Software Craftsperson

⊠ tamara@tamouse.org 1 tamouse.org **y** tamouse tamouse

Summary

Deeply experienced in software design and development methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of software quality, web applications, user experience, and team building.

Skills

general software engineering, web development,

dev-ops, business analysis, consulting,

Rails, Sinatra, Django, Flask

frameworks

facilitating, teaching

architecture, full-stack, backend, APIs,

frontend, low-level design, coding, deengineering

bugging, testing, tool chains

web libraries

React, Redux, iQuery, GraphQL, Angular (1.x), Apollo, Bootstrap,

Knockout, Backbone

databases PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, Mon-

goDB, Cassandra, Redis

languages

Ruby, JavaScript, Perl, C/C++, Shell,

Python 3, PHP, HTML5, CSS3,

SCSS/SASS, HAML

servers nginx, unicorn, puma, Apache, lighttpd

testing Minitest, RSpec, Cucumber, Capybara,

mine, Karma, Protractor

Guard, Jest, Enzyme, Mocha, Chai, Jas-

tools Emacs, Webstorm, RubyMine, bundler, rake, webpack, babel, npm, gulp, make

Ansible, Chef, Puppet, Vagrant, Docker, dev ops

Travis CI, Circle CI

operating

Linux, Mac OS X

systems

Methods Program architecture and design; User-/task-centered design; Test-/behaviour-driven development; Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything: integration, testing, deployment; Precision elicitation and facilitation, communication for action

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2 GPA.

Additional Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neurolinguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on Angular, React, Webpack, others

Experience

2017-present API-driven Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Implement modern GraphQL APIs in Ruby for the Kickerv product, and develop replacement React web client using GraphQL interface with Apollo Client.

- work on the Kickserv product
- build robust APIs to enable modern web client applications for desktop and mobile to access backend data
- o migrate API to use GraphQL in Ruby
- o create a React web client using Apollo to talk GraphQL to the back end application
- fix defects in existing frontend software
- work with other engineers to build common components

2001-Present **Web Developer**, Tamara Temple Web Development (Pontiki Software Crafts), Mendota Heights, Minnesota.

Freelance web design and development, including pro bono work for non-profits and individuals desiring a presence on the Web. Includes finding hosting space, development of information architecture, design layout of site, development and/or repurposing of content, and maintenance. Work in Perl, PHP, Ruby on Rails, JavaScript, jQuery, Backbone.JS, AngularJS (1.x), Node.js, React, Redux, GraphQL (Apollo), CSS, Sass, Postgresql, MySQL, SQLite, Apache, nginx, lighttpd, Linux, Mac OS X.

- \circ User experience and User-centered design for interactive web sites
- Database design for dynamic web sites and applications
- Creation and developing on frameworks for generating static web sites
- Frameworks and infrastructure to implement business logic and web site features
- Environments and tools for development, testing, integration and deployment
- Teach and coach new developers
- Volunteer mentor/coach/instructor for Rails.MN, RubyBridge, Twin Cities Rails hack night

2015-present **Volunteer, TA, Mentor**, Girl Develop It, Minneapolis Chapter, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Volunteer to help women learn web skills in HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Git, and publishing.

- Teaching Assistant in several classes
- Lead Tuesday "Toast and Tech" sessions to help people study and work on projects
- Teach various classes, including: "Stylin With Sass", "Falling in Love With Git"

2014-2017 Organizer, Rails.MN Beginners meetup, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Train people new to Ruby on Rails how to develop web applications using the Rails framework.

- Teach monthly classes
- Provide resources and support for students
- Maintain web resources

2016-2017 Contract Software Developer, Software for Good, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Provide software to enable clients to query a large datastore with natural language and return meaningful datasets.

- write anisble and shell scripts to deploy project to staging
- write training questions and entity extraction code

- o write extraction, transfer, and load scripts for external data
- o provide code review and expertise to other project members
- Wrote mainly in Python

2013-2016 Contract Software Developer, Ackmann-Dickenson, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Contract development in the areas of Rails and JavaScript on several A-D projects.

- Pro subscriptions and e-commerce in Brewtoad
- One-button recipe ordering in Brewtoad
- Customer Onboarding
- Micro-service architecture and implementation
- Angular SPA clients for MSA backend
- Massive and complex data analysis product
- O Data ETL middle layer to provide a massive speed-up for an e-commerce website
- Lots of Ruby on Rails and JavaScript

1980-present Various positions, Hewlett-Packard, Shopzilla, NovuHealth, BluewaterBrand.

Career as a software developer, business analyst, process and technology consultant, author, facilitator, trainer

- Web development in PHP, JavaScript, Ruby on Rails
- Software development on unix system software
- Taught relationship-based skills to engineers, managers, and senior execs.
- Consulted with various software development groups within Hewlett-Packard to improve software development capabilities
- O Developed software for network management at Hewlett-Packard
- Software Quality Engineer manager of 10 engineers
- Software Quality Engineer